A Guide to the Raymond B. Fosdick papers FA070
Rockefeller Archive Center
Raymond B. Fosdick papers
1919-1951, bulk 1919-1934
1919-1934
Rockefeller Archive Center
Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine) (1883-1972)
Institute of Social and Religious Research
Interchurch World Movement of North America
FA070
0.62 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box and 1 half-legal document box
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Raymond B. Fosdick Papers were given to the Rockefeller Family Office by Raymond B. Fosdick and were transferred to the Rockefeller Archive Center on February 2, 1981.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
Raymond B. Fosdick was born in Buffalo, New York, on June 9, 1883. He received a B.A. (1905) and M.A. (1906) from Princeton University and took his LL.D. from New York Law School in 1908. In 1910 he married Winifred Finley. She and their two children died in 1932. Fosdick married again in 1936 to Elizabeth Miner.
Prior to 1920, Fosdick held a variety of positions, including Assistant Corporation Council for New York City, Investigator of European police systems for the Bureau of Social Hygiene, and Under Secretary to the League of Nations. It was during this time that he began his life-long association with John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
From 1920 to 1936, he was a member of the legal firm Curtis, Fosdick, and Belknap and served as legal council for John D. Rockefeller, Jr. It was in this capacity that he became involved with the Interchurch World Movement and the Institute for Social and Religious Research.
Fosdick was active in various Rockefeller philanthropies from 1921 to 1948, including The Rockefeller Foundation, the General Education Board, the International Education Board, the China Medical Board, the China Medical Board, Inc., the International Health Board, The Davison Fund, and The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial.
Among his most important publications were "European Police Systems," "Story of The Rockefeller Foundation," "John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - A Portrait," "Adventure in Giving: The Story of the General Education Board," and "Chronicle of a Generation."
Raymond B. Fosdick died on July 18, 1972.
For further information concerning the life and career of Raymond B. Fosdick, see his autobiography "Chronicle of a Generation" and Daryl L. Revoldt's unpublished dissertation "Raymond B. Fosdick: Reform, Internationalism, and The Rockefeller Foundation," University of Akron, 1982.
Scope and Contents
The Raymond B. Fosdick papers focus on his activities with the Interchurch World Movement (IWM) and the Institute for Social and Religious Research (ISRR). There are no personal papers.
The Interchurch World Movement was launched in 1919 by the Board of Foreign Missions and other evangelical churches in the United States and Canada "to present a unified program of Christian service and to unite the Protestant churches of North America in the performance of their common task." To determine what needs faced the churches, survey teams were scattered all over the world, with studies in over 2,000 counties in the United States alone. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. quickly became interested in the interdenominational movement and was elected to the executive committee, as well as to the review board that evaluated the surveys.
Within a year the Movement was in financial trouble. A Businessman's Executive Committee consisting of Raymond B. Fosdick, James M. Speers, and Trevor Arnett, was brought in to straighten out the IWM's financial affairs. When it became apparent the IWM was hopelessly overextended, Fosdick was authorized to supervise the dissolution of the Movement and see that all debts were paid. The IWM closed its office in 1922 and was officially dissolved in 1924.
In 1921, at the urging of Raymond B. Fosdick, John R. Mott, and Ernest D. Burton, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. funded the continuation of certain surveys of the now defunct Interchurch World Movement. The Committee for Social and Religious Research was established to administer these surveys. In 1923 the name was changed to the Institute for Social and Religious Research and the area of study was enlarged to include "investigations in any part of the world, and in reference to any phase of the life of society which in important ways affects or is affected by organized religion." Fosdick served as the Institute's treasurer from 1921 to 1926.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. discontinued funding the ISRR in 1932. When the organization closed in 1934, it had a total of 77 projects to its credit, including "Town and Country Church in the United States," "World Missionary Atlas," and "Middletown."
Arrangement
The Raymond B. Fosdick papers are divided into two series:
Series 1 - Interchurch World Movement Series 2 - Institute for Social and Religious Research
Religion; Social sciences -- Research
- Interchurch World Movement, 1919-1951, bulk 1919-1925; 1919-1925; 1; 0.24 Cubic Feet 1 half-legal document box
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes general correspondence, financial records, and reports documenting Fosdick's work to dissolve the Interchurch World Movement. Also included in the records is correspondence concerning the controversial IWM report on the 1920 U.S. Steel Corporation Strike. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Certificates of Incorporation; By-laws (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1920-1951, bulk 1920-1925; 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Steel Strike Report, 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Financial Irregularities, 1921-1924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Financial Statements and Audits, 1919-1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1920-1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reports, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Institute for Social and Religious Research, 1921-1934; 2; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  This series includes general correspondence from Fosdick's tenure as treasurer of the Institute, a set of minutes, and a history of the ISRR. Studies conducted by the ISRR specifically mentioned in the correspondence include Middletown, Mt. Desert Island Parish, Maine Study, Study of Orientals on the Pacific Coast, and College Study. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert S. Lynd, and Hilda L. Ives.
  - History, 1921-1934 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - By-laws (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1921 January 5-1924 June 27-28 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1924 October 24-25-1928 May 18 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1928 June 27-1934 October 20 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General Correspondence, 1921-1923 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - General Correspondence, 1924-1931 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Small City Study - Middletown (Muncie, Indiana), 1924-1926 (Box 2, Folder 15)